[Music]
Hello and welcome to History Pod.
On the 5th of December 1952,
the Great Smog of London descended on
the British capital due to a combination
of air pollution and weather conditions.
To maximize revenues in the aftermath of
the Second World War, the British
government had opted to export the
country's better quality hard coal and
retain the more sulfurous lowgrade coal
for domestic consumption. Smoke from
burning this coal in domestic fires to
offset the particularly cold winter of
combined with pollutants from Greater
London's numerous power stations,
factories, and public transport to
create a thick, noxious blanket of smog
over the city.
The thick yellow black smog was held
over London for more than 4 days due to
the arrival of a high pressure weather
system. This caused an antiscyclone that
stopped the polluted air from rising
into the atmosphere.
Windless conditions and London's
position in a river valley also meant
that the smog was unable to be blown
away.
Visibility in the city was reduced to
just a few meters, bringing public
transport to a halt and forcing schools
and businesses to close.
Meanwhile, people across the city
breathed in the toxic air and began to
succumb to respiratory infections.
Cattle at the Smithfield show at Earl's
Court reportedly suffocated. And while
nobody made the connection until several
months after the smog had lifted,
estimates state that between 4 and
12,000 Londoners died as a direct result
of breathing the polluted air.
In response, the government began to
rethink its policy towards air pollution
and in 1956
introduced the Clean Air Act that
established smoke control areas where
only clean fuels could be burned,
precipitating a shift towards the use of
cleaner coals, electricity, and gas as
sources of heat.
[Music]